Amen. So, let me get straight to the
word of God and I want to share with you
types of battles or battles of life.
Battles of life. I'm going to take my
time on this topic and I'll encourage
you. These are theme that can take us
around 2 to 3 months as we try to
expound on it and I'm going to take my
time because we are in this life and
everyone is going to fight this life.
And there are battles in life that must
be fought and they must be won. I
discovered in this life, it's either
right now you are in a battlefield or
you are out of battle or you are getting
into battle.
It is either you are in battle now or
out of a battle or you are getting into
a battle. And so, life the day you got
born again, you got recruited into a
battlefield. Whether you like it or not,
there are battles to fight and there are
victories also that the Lord has assured
and guaranteed us. We were not called as
a diplomatic entity. We were called as
warriors in the kingdom of El Elyon. And
the Bible says them that overcome shall
sit with me. So, them that overcome are
them that sit. And I want to share the
10 battles that every believer will
fight.
fight. Battle number one is called the
battle of the Lord. Battle of the Lord.
Battle of the Lord. This is a battle
that is beyond your ability and
capacity, but it is in the level of God.
We will take time to look at every
battle individually. The second battle
is the battle of divine backup or the
battle of reinforcement.
The battle of divine backup or the
battle of reinforcement
where God comes to give you backup.
Sometimes you show up in battle and the
battle intensifies and God shows up and
he begins to fight with you. That means
you must be in the battlefield. This is
a battle you can't escape, but the Lord
shows up to fight with you and fight for
you.
Number three is what I call the battle
of elevation.
The battle of elevation.
Goliath was not a giant to pray out.
Goliath was a giant to fight out and
slay out.
It was after David fought Goliath that
women began to sing, David has slain
10,000. The popularity of David was
connected to the battle of Goliath. Are
you getting me?
There are battles that announce you.
Number four, there is the battle of
destiny.
The battle of destiny. In this battle,
you deal with adversities.
Adversities. Adversities. What is an
adversity?
What is an adversity?
An adversity
is a perennial opposition.
A perennial opposition.
And this opposition is not repentant.
They never repent.
When you are dealing with people like
witches
when you are dealing with
opposition that is forever there, it is
called a battle of destiny.
And this is a battle whereby one has to
live. You either live or the witch
lives.
Hallelujah.
Then there is number five, the battle of
the heavenlies.
The battle of the heavenlies. The
heavens. The heavens. The battle of the
heavenlies.
We see this in Daniel. We see this in
Revelation.
We see this in the book of Chronicles.
Wars in the heavens and they interfere
with our earth.
Then number seven, there is
battles of territories.
Battles of territories.
Ah, some of you have no biro
no notebook.
If it's not on paper, it's vapor.
Yes?
I'm on number six.
Which one have I jumped?
Okay, so I'll come to it. So, that's
number six, battle of territories.
If you sit the next to neighbor who
looks like a delegate, tell them
neighbor
tell them neighbor
next time
please come with a notebook
and a biro.
Don't come as a delegate.
Hallelujah.
Amen. Amen.
So, there is battles of territories.
Everyone under the sound of my voice the
Lord has anointed you for a territory.
There is a mountain to conquer.
The pulpit is too small for all of us.
But there are pulpits where you are. In
the marketplace, in governance, in all
these areas, there is a pulpit for you.
And until you master your territory you
have no relevance on earth.
Are we together? So, you are not a
tourist on earth. You are a history
maker.
There are things that must change
because you showed up.
The Bible says in the book of Genesis,
and there was no rain because God had
not caused it to rain because there was
no man to till the land. Meaning that
the heavens could not pour because man
has not showed up. There are things that
cannot happen because you have not
showed up.
There is a territory to conquer.
Are we together? I am conquering mine as
a pastor. You have to conquer yours.
Some of you God will raise you as
billionaires and millionaires for the
kingdom.
That's a territory. We'll look at that
matter intensively and look at the seven
mountains of our influence.
There is the battle within a battle.
Number seven. A battle within a
a battle.
Sometimes
there is what I call the main battle
but there is another battle that shows
up to disrupt you from the main battle.
A good example, David shows up in the
battlefield to fight Goliath. But the
brothers begin to fight David.
So, in this battle, you might waste your
energy, resources
fighting the wrong battle and fail to
fight the right battle.
May the Lord give you intelligence to
audit your battles.
Some battles you win by silence.
Silence can never be misquoted.
Sometimes just shut up.
It is not every cry that needs a
response.
Silence
is louder sometimes than words.
Some of us our mouth have cost us a lot.
Selah.
Then there is the battle of the mind.
The battle of the mind.
These are operations that take place in
your mind. Mawazo.
Tormentations.
Things that try to rise above the
knowledge of Jesus.
This is the genesis of depression.
Anxieties.
They are thieves of life.
Everyone has a what if.
You want to begin a business, but there
is what if it could do that.
Because there is battle. Someone wrote a
book, it was called the battlefield of
the mind.
And then there is what I call number
nine, the battle to the mind.
There is the battle of That means hiyoni
vita inatendeka kwa akili yako.
Niende nisiende.
Nifanye nisifanye.
Hallelujah.
There are battles that happen in the
mind.
Decisions that you need to make, but
there is also a battle to to to the
mind. These are external voices.
Job fought this battle. Three men sat by
Job and they began to make Job analyze
and they were saying, you must have
sinned. You can't face what you are
facing if you never sinned. And the last
voice was the voice of the wife, curse
God and leave.
Environmental sound. Things that come
from outside.
I remember one day I
I was so frustrated.
I was in town
and I met a friend of mine
who used to copy my work in class.
Very successful.
And all I was doing was missionary work
and the man had a big hustle, a good
machine.
And I looked at his life and I felt like
I've wasted my life. All my money I used
to use it in ministry.
And the worst question you can have is
when you meet with colleagues you are
with with campus and you are smarter
than them or in high school and they ask
you, so squeeze uko wapi?
And he asked that question.
And I said, my mission.
And I could see the the the expression
of why waste all this education.
You'll ungeacha to form
And I remember I was so frustrated.
And I began to ask, am I really doing
the right thing? There are voices that
can discourage you.
And I remember I went to battle shop. I
was seated there, discouraged.
And as I sat there, this couple came and
they were taking measurements for their
wedding garments.
And they told me what the lady told me,
pastor, I got born again in Pangani
girls in form two in a meeting you are
preaching. They were Jesus family.
That was Millie.
And at that hour, the Lord told me, you
may not have a big car, but these men
are your medals.
Are you getting me? And some of you,
there are so many voices.
People see you as a madman.
When you share your vision, we will come
to that matter.
Are we together? I will share secrets of
incubation.
When a woman is pregnant,
the first phase, you don't see the
pregnancy.
But the moment she reaches 5, 6 months,
she cannot hide.
Let your pregnancy announce itself.
Don't convince men when it is in
inception level.
Elizabeth was told she's barren.
I tell you the day it was 6 month, that
is the day she went to see Mary.
At this level, we cannot argue.
And I can see her walking style.
The battle. Them that called her barren.
Okay.
Tell your neighbor, neighbor,
don't shout before it manifest.
Some of you are shouting too much and
that's where attacks came.
And then we have
the battle of diversion and destruction.
The battle of diversion and destruction.
We will find this in the story of
Nehemiah. It is called the battle of
Onno
or oh no.
So, there are things God wants you to
make, build, and do all these things,
but someone diverts your focus by
introducing battle and you abandon the
very thing you are called to do.
Hallelujah.
So, we are going to handle every battle
individually.
We will build on this because this is
deliverance to some people.
And then we are going to look at the
secrets of winning battles.
Secrets of winning battles, and there
are five of them unless the Lord adds as
we continue. The first secret is the
secret of divine intelligence.
Divine intelligence. Tell your neighbor,
neighbor, after this series, you will be
an FBI in the spirit.
Hallelujah.
You know, I love action movies.
Have you ever seen the star in going to
a territory?
And then he's there, he's leading with a
gun. And then he comes a place and say,
and then he checks around, he checks
around,
and then he says, let's go.
Discernment.
Intelligence.
Some of you, you'll be walking and then
say, hold. No, no, hold.
Let's scan the atmosphere.
You enter places, you can pick signals
in the spirit.
The Bible says, and Elisha had the
ability to hear the conversation of the
king of Assyria in his bedroom.
That's a CIA in the spirit.
>> [laughter]
>> Tell your neighbor, neighbor, these are
good levels.
Hallelujah.
The second one is divine strategies.
And we will look at the strategy of
Gideon.
Battles are won on strategy.
You don't win battles because of the
power of your weapons.
You win battles because of the power of
your strategy.
Do you know how the battle began in
Israel and Palestine?
Yes?
You see, what happens is the
Palestinians have underground channels
and underground routes. So, anytime they
are fighting, their men go underground.
And no matter how Israel strikes them,
they can't attack them. So, this is what
Israel did, strategy. They came with
their bulldozers to the border, Gaza.
They began to
put them put their engines on
room room room. And all
the Palestinians went underground, then
they bombed them there.
The Hamas
strategy.
Uh sisisifu vita, please don't get me
wrong.
I am just giving an example that is very
late, amen, latest. Because I was
following that war.
And I was waiting for newspaper
eschatologist. And I knew someone will
come and tell us the war of Armageddon
is about to come. These are small
battles. These are called geopolitics.
Oh, we thank you, back you for free
education. Our geopolitics means there
is a geological geographical terrain
that has politics on it.
Because whoever controls Gaza has
opportunity in terms of trade.
Now, the West need Israel where it is.
Israel was planted there by Britain.
So that they can be a point of contact
to pick intelligence of Arab nations.
That's why they are surrounded by Arab
nations. This is where they pick
intelligence. If today there is war
between America and Iran, they will
fight from Israel. That's why they need
Israel.
And that's why Iran and the other Arab
nations need Gaza because they are also
a point of intelligence. So, this is not
about Israel and Gaza. This is about
intelligence of nations that need a
place of war. It is called geopolitics.
And so, when there is geopolitics, you
look for topics that connect and divide.
One of them is religion. This is Islam,
this is Christian. Indoctrinate them
with the concept of covenant land of
Abraham. Let them pray as we are doing
our politics.
I prayed for Israel and I prayed for
Palestine.
Both of them need God.
Okay.
Hallelujah. I know there are scriptures
that say pray for the peace of
Israel, but that can be debated another
day.
Because we don't know who is Israel. Is
it that Israel or are we the Israel, the
church, the new Israel?
So, the peace of the church, could it be
the peace of Israel? Or is it that
Israel? Can that Israel, can we look at
them through genealogy that those men
who are there with big beards and specs
and a cap that they are true Jews?
Can we confirm? Because the last time
they were scattered, 70 AD, they were
scattered globally and they were
gathered in 1945. So, all that time, can
we prove you are a Jew or are you a man
exercising Judaism?
These are technical questions. We don't
have the Urim and Thummim. Neither do we
have the genealogy that you can stand
and say I'm a Jew and we look at the
Urim and Thummim where the light will
pass and say this one is a Jew.
So, there are people, even black men,
exercising Judaism. There is a Jewish
church in Nairobi. Those are black Jews.
Okay.
That's for another day. When we mature,
we can debate.
So, let me not introduce you to debate.
Let's chew what we can handle. Tell your
neighbor, mature quickly.
So that we can handle some matter.
Hallelujah.
Jesus. So, there is strategy. Tell your
neighbor, strategy.
Number three, we have revelations of our
weapons.
If the Bible says, the weapons of our
warfare
not weapons. So, there are weapons
are not carnal,
but they are strong, mighty by the
pulling down of strongholds.
So, what does that mean? There are
weapons.
So, is the blood of Jesus supposed to be
applied on roads?
What is the place of the blood?
Okay.
Tell your neighbor we'll come to the
weapons.
The finger of God, the hook of God.
They are serious weapons in this
kingdom. We will enter into the armory
of God
and understand how equipped we are. So
that the next time you see a witch,
you will not run away. You will know the
weapon to engage.
The church is not a place where we come
to
gather because we are defeated. It's a
gathering of victorious men.
We need to know.
Some of us are running away from a devil
that has a blunt penknife.
And they are running away with an AK-47.
You can see that race in the spirit.
Because the devil marketed penknife at
the expense of AK-47.
So, we were told how powerful and
sharper penknife is. No one told you the
weapon you have, it is so powerful that
a man with a penknife is the one who
ought to flee.
So, in the church, men are fleeing.
We need revelation of the weapons. They
are many.
The fire of God. And you see, what
happens again, you can't use a bazooka
to shoot a mosquito. There there is
there is reasonable applicable of
weapons.
When I see you there
What are DJ Afro?
Now I want to know what I want.
Not a mosquito on a time.
They are small demons that need
discipline.
They don't even need prayer. Just be
disciplined. Keep time. They will never
attack you.
They don't need fasting. Just
discipline.
And they are demons that need serious
armory.
So, we need to understand them.
War also we need to have
timing. You need to know when to launch
out.
People don't just fight anytime.
This is where the concept of prayer
hours come.
>> [snorts]
>> There are hours that carry sacrifice.
Sacrifices.
Midnight prayers.
It is not that that hour, of course, we
will look at the watches and the
spiritual significance of that. Because
there is a level of intelligence that
comes to the time you pray.
But that does not mean that if you pray
in the morning, it doesn't count. Are
you getting me?
But there are prayers that cost you.
They carry weight.
They are prayers that are made out of
comfort and convenience.
But they are prayers that are made out
of sacrifice.
Those prayers carry weight in the
spirit.
Hallelujah.
And we'll look at the point of we don't
pray because we feel like.
We buzzing at your feeling you could
pray. Hi. There are many things you
don't feel like. I don't want to go to
job. Guess what? It's Monday. Many of
you don't feel like going to job.
Now you don't want to go to work.
So, we don't live life by what we feel.
It's what we ought to. That's why Jesus
said, "Men ought to pray." He never said
"Men need to pray when they feel like."
It's ought. It's a necessity. Just like
food.
We will look so look at number five.
Study the enemy patterns.
Every enemy has a pattern.
Every enemy has
some battles have patterns. And when you
are able to destabilize the pattern,
uh you will know it.
In the first service, I shared the story
of how my wife and I will go to sauna
every Sunday morning.
We are driving, listening to worship.
And worship is listening to us. Amen.
>> [snorts]
>> You know that moment you try to put
gospel songs, but the matter is heavy.
And we used to disagree on very small
matters. Very very I don't want to say
small cuz maybe they are major to her,
but later we realized they were very
small. And I will come to church and
sometimes very sad, feeling not very
okay. Until we came to a place and we
said, "Let us be fighting on Monday."
And we've never fought on Monday. Amen.
So, don't don't begin to intercede for
us tomorrow. So, my pastor come on a
bigger than a Monday. What you do stand
in the gap? No.
But what I discovered is that
as a minister, when you stand on the
pulpit to declare the word of God, the
nature of your heart is paramount.
Because the message carries the spirit.
Are you getting me? So, the devil could
not fight the message, but the devil
made sure the spirit is not the same.
I will preach powerful things.
I should sit here and not say amen.
Now I don't know if many of you are
sleeping or you are not moral to
continue. When I see you there
Cuz you know, even if all of you leave,
I know there's one member who will not
leave.
It is her.
When I see you there So, so there was a
pattern. And guess what? It was very
easy just to check.
Why do we fight on Sundays? So, let's
begin to pray on Sundays. So, that this
thing does not show up. And the pattern
ended.
So, there are patterns demonically
that when you study them, you are able
to seize the fire.
Are we together?
And then finally, we are going to see on
how to sustain victory.
Victory is good, but how do you sustain
it?
The first wisdom is you have to build a
defense system.
You have to build a defense system.
The reason why we have army in Kenya
is because we have enemies and people
that can be our enemy anytime. So, we
don't wait for them to attack. We have a
defense.
There are people right now in Mandera
walking with guns, just checking.
Just in case an enemy decides to launch
out, they are ready to fire. Defense
system. Hallelujah.
The second one, there is another one
called offense system.
The system of offense.
Sometimes you don't wait for the enemy
to attack. You are the one that takes
violence
in the kingdom of the enemy.
Since the days of John the Baptist, the
kingdom suffereth.
So, we are the ones that carry the
violence.
And we take it to the enemy.
There are times you go for your goods
without negotiation.
Jesus did it.
When Jesus
came out of the cross,
he descended,
took the keys, and set the captives
free.
He took the violence to the enemy.
There are times you need to descend
before you ascend.
Are you getting me?
There's something I was I'm planning to
do. It's very personal. It's on a
personal level.
And I was engaging God and was asking
God, "Do you want me to do it now?
Or do you want me to do it later?"
And there there is an assignment that
God gave me over my family.
And I know God told me you're going to
deal with the spirit of poverty.
And I asked him, "Do you want me to do
now?" And the Lord told me, "The reason
why there is opposition in the spirit is
because whatever you are about to do
will break something in the spirit."
So, I knew it is not just an action.
It is an announcement in the spirit that
this realm is open to others.
Are you getting me?
That's why there are things that come
upon you. Because when you break forth,
you open a new dimension.
Number three, you stay alert always.
This is what we call sustained
surveillance mode.
Stay alert always.
Your eyes are forever watching.
You are on the tower.
When you go to a military barracks,
there is always a soldier on the tower.
They are alert.
The last time the military messed up, we
lost more than 50 soldiers
in Somalia.
And they say a car came,
entered into the camp,
and then a young boy came
with a cup, and the young boy was the
spy.
And the young boy, you know, a very
young child, picked the intelligence,
and the young child left. And they gave
the status. And our soldiers were were
not very alert. And that night they were
attacked.
And they lost men. So, we don't lose our
surveillance because we have ground.
Are you getting me? That's why don't
stop praying because you got a job.
Hi. Where? Where?
It's going to be a service or notice
without reasons.
I'm being anyway, your services are
good. You are competent. But we are
sorry. We are cutting down. I don't know
what you are talking about. Then now you
become them crystal aqualida. You keep
on running to prayer.
So, my don't go to my home B. It
should be vice versa. You stay in
prayer.
There was no amen. Meaning that I have
many culprits.
What I should do to okay where where
heavens get?
God is not going to give you something
big.
I should not give you anything. Heavens
get sick with that. Because I don't want
to retire. After the matter comes down,
where where Netflix?
Another three months.
Who can scare come to go to go?
Now, will you live like that?
You better stay in a place
where you reign and you sustain victory.
Are you getting me?
Matters should not take you to prayer.
You need to be in a place whereby you
address matters before they come.
There [snorts] is only one thing that
you can send ahead of you, and it's not
money. It's your prayer.
When I saw you
the first week of June, which we are
going to do, now we secure the next six
months.
There's something you can send ahead,
which is called prayer.
My village pastor told me how could I
just be in a home B?
Sometimes we pray for future.
There are times I sense grace for study,
and I always know God is working
something. And there are times I have no
time to study. I'm from one meeting to
the other, and I rely on the archives of
studies and prayers that I made. Do you
have an archive of prayer that can keep
you sustained when matters are urgent?
Now when you want to go to work in a
ship
I'm making for Saudi Arabia to go to
work and come back slide.
Tell your neighbor neighbor.
I'm excess.
Are we together?
You will come. A time will come you may
be too busy, but there is archives of
prayers that sustain you sometime.
Number four, always improve your
weapons.
Strategies of war, improve your weapons.
There is a There is a place where the
Bible says a new God came. So those new
gods needed new weapons.
And number five,
once in a while you need to roll in the
spirit.
Once in a while you need to
roll.
This is marking your territory.
Marking your territory. Rolling in the
spirit.
Laban, there's something you have done
to my sound. I don't know if you touched
it
or what happened.
Am I still level?
Okay, then my sound from inside
has a problem.
Let's begin with the first battle, the
battle of the Lord. Are you learning
something?
Are you learning something?
The battle of the Lord. This one I'll
take time. I'm your pastor. I'll stay
with you for long.
You know when you go as a guest preacher
and you have a message that we want
service.
What is the battle of the Lord? What is
the battle of the Lord? The battle of
the Lord, number one, is a battle that
is in the level of God.
It is in the level of God.
The battle of the Lord is in the battle
that is in the level of
God. Why am I saying this? Because
number two,
there are battles that are beyond your
ability and capacity. That's a fact.
These are battles that are above your
weapons
and your arsenals that you have in
engagement.
They are called battles of the Lord.
So they are battles that are in God
level.
They are above your ability and capacity
and they are above your weapons and your
arsenals. Are we together?
Are we together?
And everyone in life will come through a
battle that is above them.
Allow me to share a story.
When we were
Oh, Mama Gift was there. Mama Gift is
one of the elders of this church.
She knows our story.
When we were
second Sunday of our service, we had a
visitation and it was not divine. It was
diviners.
70 of them came.
A young pastor in a new territory and
they went in the city and said,
You know that language?
So I said what we want to say.
And I remember
I was a young pastor. I asked God, what
should I do? I don't know. The Lord told
me number one, they wanted you to deny
them the opportunity because these are
men that have a voice in the city so
that they can attack the church and say
to
come back to the new church.
You know you are a new pastor. Nobody
knows you and people are looking for
your intelligence. So I said name a
homie.
Jesus.
This place didn't I call the tiles. So
they came.
70 of them, around 70.
I think we were only three, Pastor Ken,
Mama Gift and me. We went to a hotel
Silver Spoon. We ate. I made a prayer
out of fear, not faith.
I told the Lord, if these are your
servants, let them use the altar. If
these are not your servants, preserve
the altar and that was my sign.
I came I sat I invited them.
>> [snorts]
>> The person that ran the meeting stood
here.
She never left that area. She was
arrested by the Holy Ghost.
I knew this battle is beyond me. How do
I engage 70 diviners?
Then they came and told me, "Pastor, we
saw you 10 years ago.
We knew you were coming.
10 years, I was not very serious even in
salvation.
But they saw me. How do you fight such a
battle?
They said to me on a poster to come join
me
10 years ago.
They are battles that are above you.
Are we together? I knew I have no power.
My prayer at that time I responded and I
told the Lord I said this church is not
mine. I surrender it to you. They did
things, they prophesied, but the Lord
confirmed his word. He preserved the
altar.
A month later, we found chicken
slaughtered outside there.
And then there was another one outside
in another garage. The owner of the
garage died that Sunday at 3:00. God
preserved us. He fought for us.
Because we have a blood that is greater.
At time I was praying I was suicidal.
And I'm anointed.
Standing at my balcony and you listen.
The battle of the mind.
And I love life. Let me tell you I love
life.
My wife was asleep. A thought was just
crisscrossing. I felt discouraged. I
felt defeated and it's not that the
church was not working. I could not
point to a specific thing that was
making me feel discouraged, but there
was such a demonic discouragement and at
that time the Lord opened my eyes and I
saw men gathering the diviners. They
were in their shrine in a table cursing
me. The Lord told me speak [music] in
tongues. The battle was beyond me and
the Lord told me, "From today I will
hide you. They will never see you."
There is a battle we cannot fight. There
is a battle that is in the level of our
Lord. By our ability we are defeated.
There are times men gather and we know
that we know we are not sufficient in
prayer. At that is the hour to know
victory young.
Psalms 46:10.
This is what the Bible says.
Everyone here has that battle. Are you
getting me?
I tell you you will come through it in
life.
When I discuss a fair with a small
secretary,
how do you fight the board?
CEO, please.
How do you approach the board?
They've gathered against you.
And you look at this meeting and you
say, "Lord,
it's beyond me, beyond my networks,
beyond my connections, beyond my money,
beyond even my prayer. They are the ones
who run the company, but God fight for
me." Psalms 46:10.
This is what the Bible says, "Be still
and know that I am God." Everybody read.
"Be still and know that I am
I will be exalted among the nations. I
will be exalted in the
The The Psalms 46
was written out of an encounter in the
book of Second Chronicles chapter 20.
From verse 1 to 30. The battle of
Jehoshaphat
and the armies of Ammon,
the Moabites
and as a man who dwelt in the mountain.
Are you getting me? Are you getting me?
So the language here is be still. What
does that mean? Don't move.
What does that mean? There is battle.
Your sword can't deliver you.
Your intelligence can't get you out. So
what do I do? I just stay still and know
that he is God because there is a level
of knowing God where you know he has no
history of losing war.
He has no history of losing any battle.
This is where you begin to know the
battle is not mine, but the battle is of
the Lord because whatever is being
fought is that which God called me to
do.
The Bible says one day they took Peter
to jail.
They had beheaded James
and Herod is a spirit we call a Herod
spirit. It is the same spirit that
operated with Pharaoh that assassinates
carriers of revival.
So Herod rose, beheaded James
and it saw that it pleased the people.
He arrested the one that carried the
keys, Peter.
How do you arrest a key man
with the keys? Oh, that's a rhyme.
A key man with the keys.
So they arrested Peter,
but the Bible says they took him in jail
and there were four cores of soldiers.
These are four
levels, ranks of men that were guarding
the jail.
It was during the Passover season and
the Bible says and Peter was asleep in
jail
while James had been beheaded. It took
an angel to slap Peter.
The man was deep asleep. An angel
slapped him and said, "I have come for
thee." The man was asleep in jail
knowing that James has lost his head.
That is the level of being still. What
does that mean? The waters are still
ravaging. I can hear the cries of war in
the territories, but I know it's beyond
me.
Come on, you guys. Speak your level. Oh,
may God keep you for long.
Oh, Jesus.
Let me I I admire your faith, but some
of us have reached that level. Come by
and by. Kilikita happen here. Kilikita
happen.
And that's where the Bible says be still
and know that I'm God. Can we read this
scripture quickly and get a couple of
things? Tell your neighbor, neighbor,
the stomach is for food and food for
stomach and both will be devoured in
hell. And tell that neighbor it's in the
Bible. Hallelujah.
Let's go to 2 Chronicles chapter number
1.
We are going to read a long scripture
and then we analyze this matter. And I
want us to read like Sunday school
because I want us to I want to teach I
want to teach. I'm not in a hurry. Are
you getting me? I want to teach. I want
to teach you to a level that one day you
can open your book and teach another
person.
Are we together?
Everybody [snorts] read. After Okay, it
happened this that the people of Moab
with the people of Ammon and others with
them besides the Ammonite came to battle
against
So we are seeing there was an alliance.
And they were coming to fight against
one man. Who was Jehoshaphat?
The name Jehoshaphat means Yahweh
judges.
God judges.
And Jehoshaphat was the fourth king of
Judah.
Because remember Solomon, the kingdom
divided, Judah and Israel. And there was
Rehoboam and Jeroboam.
We need to read our Bibles. I don't like
the way you're looking at me.
There was Rehoboam and
Jeroboam and this man came after Abijah
and Asa.
So we have Jehoshaphat as the fourth
king of Judah.
Now people have made an alliance to come
and fight him.
Because the kings are the ones that led
men to war.
So they were coming to fight Israel, but
this battle was a battle of kings.
And [snorts] anytime we are talking
about battles of kings, it's a language
of territory.
So they were not coming for peace. They
were coming to dethrone, embarrass
Jehoshaphat. There was an alliance.
It is easy to fight one army, but it is
hard to deal with an alliance.
But we bless the Lord because we are
also in another alliance
with God.
With God.
They are there with the alliance, but we
have a partner in this war.
Let's go to two. Everybody read.
Verse two.
So there was a great multitude. This is
a team coming. The enemy does not
prepare you for war. No one gets a
notice of war.
They just attack and the best way to
attack is suddenly. So a man comes with
intelligence and says, "King, they are
coming. They have gathered. In their
thousands they are coming." And see the
response of the king. Verse three. Let's
all read quickly.
And Jehoshaphat feared and set himself
to seek the Lord and proclaim a fast
throughout Judah. Let's look at four.
So Judah gathered together to ask help
from the Lord and from all the cities of
Judah they came to seek the Lord.
Listen, they first of all began by
seeking help from the Lord. They looked
at their weapons, looked at their
muscles and they said, "This is a war in
the level of God." They began to fast.
Fasting does not help God. It helps a
believer.
When you set yourself to fast, you are
increasing your download frequency
in the spirit.
Are we together?
Let's assume
where the altar is
is a Wi-Fi active area.
Wi-Fi active.
And
my phone
is activated. So meaning that
when I'm out of this area, there are
things I can't receive.
I have WhatsApp.
I have Facebook. I have Gmail.
But as long as I am not in the Wi-Fi
active area, they are all dumped and
numb.
It doesn't mean that they are not there,
but they are not functional. You have
the Holy Ghost.
You have ability to pray.
You have What do I call it? Ability to
hear God, but you are out of Wi-Fi.
Now what does fasting does? It
accelerates you to Wi-Fi zone
in the spirit. And the moment you get to
fast,
the the first three days are the hardest
because the flesh begins to die on day
three.
Day one at 12.
Day one of fasting.
Day two in a good 11:58. Day three in a
good 12. Day four in a good four. It is
a whole time. By day five you are dead.
And when you are dead, things begin to
activate.
Your prayers begin to be aligned.
Because day one you came with appetites
of the flesh.
By day seven you begin to receive the
burdens of the spirit.
Are you getting me?
And so what happened? Fasting
accelerates your download in the spirit.
Some things begin to get activated in
fasting.
Suddenly you can see something you never
saw.
Tell your neighbor, neighbor, fasting
does not help God.
Fasting will help you.
Tell your neighbor you cannot eat from
January to December
faithfully
and even eat tithe
and expect to defeat the devil.
It is It has never been had.
Are you getting me? So they announced a
fast. They wanted to be sharp in the
spirit, accurate in the spirit. There is
a scripture that says that this kind
does not come unless by fasting and
prayer. What was that kind? Number one,
it was a generational demon.
You can't deal with generational matters
with a Sunday prayer.
Number two, this issue,
whatever the disciples were dealing
with, was epilepsy, a spirit that
[music] cast the son down. But Jesus
came and said, "You dumb and mute." So
the disciples were not addressing the
spirit that was affecting the man.
Let me give you an example. If [snorts]
I say, "Kamau, get out." If there is no
Kamau, he will not get out.
But if I'm specific and say, "Ken Choku,
get out." I am accurate. There is a Ken
here. When Jesus looked at that child,
he knew the problem is not being cast
into fire. The problem is a dumb and
mute spirit. When the spirit leaves, the
fire issue will die.
He said, "This one can't go out." Why?
It needs accuracy in the spirit.
Lord, there is an army. They are coming
to attack. What is it you are saying in
the spirit? Let us fast as a nation.
You discover all battles in Israel were
endorsed by God.
Even your battles have to be endorsed by
God. Let's go quickly. Jesus. Ha.
Yes, that is. You're doing well, sir.
You're on the
on the mic on this
Leave there. Everybody read. Then
Jehoshaphat stood in the assembly of
Judah and Jerusalem in the house of the
Lord before the new court. Meaning that
a court was a place where men gathered.
It's like we get an overflow and we
build a shed outside there. That becomes
a new court. It is a gathering of men.
So he stood at the new court in the
house of the Lord. Let's begin to
analyze the prayer of a man that was in
war because this one will help you
analyze how you ought to pray.
Hallelujah.
Some of you look very sleepy, very
hungry, but I choose not to look at your
faces.
I choose to focus on my message.
I know we we can shout the whole
service, amen?
But this is what will make you grow.
I'm saying everybody read.
Oh Lord God of our
Are you not God in heaven, and do you
not rule over all the kingdoms of the
nation? And in your hand is there no
power and might so that no one is able
to withstand you.
Tell your neighbor, "Neighbor,
your victory in battle
is connected
to your revelation of God."
Are you getting me?
It is our revelation of who God is that
will assure our victory in war.
Some of us we have a distorted
revelation
about God.
During the midweek service, I talked
about the supremacy of Christ.
And some of us have no problem. We
believe in Christ, but I got anointing
oil.
Anointing oil in a cologne.
Ah, Jesus.
Can I bring you this is my special oil?
There is only one special anointing oil.
It's the Holy Ghost.
Are we Are you getting it? So so they
had a revelation of who God was. See,
they they began to say, "The Lord God of
our fathers, covenant keeping God. We
know you not as a covenant saying, you
are a covenant keeping God. There are
many things you can bypass, but you
can't bypass your covenant. Because a
covenant is a binding agreement between
two parties. Yes, Lord, we are the
weaker party, but you have never failed
in fulfilling your agreement. Anytime
there is a covenant with God, we can
fail. How many pledges have you ever
made to God and never honored?
And how many things did God promise you
and he still fulfilled?
Ask Abraham.
The man is told you'll have a child,
sleeps with Hagar, gets a child, and God
says, "I'll still open the womb of Sarah
because Hagar is not my child."
He doesn't fail to fulfill his part
because you have doubted him.
Let's all read quickly.
Oh Lord God of our fathers, everybody.
And do you not rule over all the
kingdoms of the nations? And in your
hand is there not power and might so
that no one is able to withdraw you.
Let's go to seven.
Everybody.
Are you not our God who drove out the
inhabitants of this land before your
people Israel and gave it to the
descendants of Abraham, your friend for
What was he saying? Lord, this land you
gave it to our fathers by covenant. So
no nation can take us out unless, oh
God, you are not a covenant keeping God.
These are levels of prayer where we call
them petition prayers.
When you are in a battle that is God
kind of battle, you must understand the
legislation
of the scripture.
Let's go quickly. Eight.
If disaster comes upon us, sword,
judgment, pestilence, or famine, we will
stand before this temple in your
presence, for your name is in this
temple, and cry out to you in our
affliction, and you will hear and
Now, this is Jehoshaphat
quoting what covenant God made with
Solomon while dedicating the temple.
He said,
"Because of this giving" There was a
giving.
"If my people call me in this altar, I
will answer."
>> [snorts]
>> There are three things that are
mentioned there.
Number one is sword.
Leave judgment. There is pestilence and
there is famine. These are the tools in
the hand of God for judgment.
Now, we need to write this down.
These are the three tools of judgment
that God uses.
Number one he uses
sword. What is sword? War.
Anytime there is war in an area, it is
fertile ground for evangelism.
Pestilence.
COVID.
Right now, there is a revival breaking
out in India.
They have begun to abandon their gods.
Indians are amazing, man.
They make their gods, and when their
gods don't serve them, they destroy them
and abandon them.
Someone said God made us in his image,
but men have made God in their own
image.
Those are Indians.
Pastor Jimmy and Pastor Ronnie have been
doing healing and revival meetings
through Zoom in India.
The pestilence there has broken the
ground.
Are we together?
Even in Kenya, there are few things.
And then there is famine.
Most of the famines in the Bible were
created.
It was not the absence of rain, that is
drought.
It was the absence of food.
Are you getting me? There is a
difference between famine and drought.
Drought is absence of rain.
But famine is when a city is besieged.
When you read about the Samaritan, the
Samaria was surrounded by the Assyrians,
and there was famine. What does that
mean? That you are surrounded by the
enemy. No one goes in, no one goes out.
So you consume
and you eat all the food and are left
with nothing, and you begin to starve.
That's famine.
So that was a tactic of judgment that
the Lord will permit the enemy to
besiege men.
Ah, are we together?
Are we together?
It is a lockdown.
So you finish the supplies in the land,
and after that,
you enter famine. These are the tools in
the hand of God for judgment.
And that's why when we see such things,
we ought to ask God. Okay.
And in your presence for your name is in
the temple, and cry out to you in your
affliction, and you will hear and
saved. Tell your neighbor, "Neighbor,
the names of the Lord
represents the character of God.
And God will defend his character."
I have 5 minutes. Let's look at 10.
>> [snorts]
>> Everybody read.
Read loudly.
So the people never attacked them when
they came from Egypt. This is an
assembly. Let's look at 10.
No, 11. Go quickly to the next one.
Here they are rewarding us by coming to
throw us out of your
which you have given us to
Are you seeing the language? They're
saying Mungu land ni yako.
So they take land yako.
Look at 12.
>> [snorts]
>> There is a joke that was going to no way
so.
By the same guy who did Allah.
That's what they're saying.
Our God, will you not judge them, for we
have no power?
When we look at our arsenals, we can't
fight this army. They are beyond us.
They are above us.
This great multitude that is coming
against us, nor do we know what to do,
but our eyes are
Tell your neighbor, "Fix your eyes on
Jesus."
Not on the enemy that is coming. Let's
look at the next one, 13. Let's all
read.
Now, all Judah with their little ones,
their wives, and their children stood
before the Lord. There is a place you
enter and you stand in the Lord but
before the Lord because at this level,
you cannot fight the battle. Look at 14.
Then the spirit of the Lord came upon
Jahaziel, the son of Zechariah, the son
of Benaiah, the son of Jaaziel, the son
of Mattaniah, a Levite of the sons of
Asaph in the midst of the assembly.
Do I have time?
1 Chronicles 25:1. Let me show you the
sons of Asaph.
This is how I fought my battles.
The sons of Asaph were a Levitical
priest that prophesied with harps and
lyres.
1 Chronicles 25:1.
25:1. Leave Satan alone.
Let's go to the generation of Asaph.
Everybody read.
And of Jeduthun, who should prophesy
with harps, stringed instruments, and
cymbals, and the number of the skilled
men performing their service. Now, we
are given the number. Tell your
neighbor, "Neighbor, this level of war
is won by our prophetic worship."
Me, I don't know about your mom.
But there are times I would hear my mom
sing some songs and I knew there is war.
She knew she cannot fight, but she would
begin to pour her heart in songs.
And at that level, she's invoking
something in the atmosphere.
There is a level where you begin to sing
prophetically. A song that gives you
energy to stand in the midst of your
enemies. Some of the most powerful
worships were not birthed in a place of
comfort. They were birthed in a place of
travail and warfare. Shut up at Aya. Oh
my God, there is a place prayer cannot
enter. It's only a song that can declare
what you are going through.
I was looking at this song that is
called Modwaire. I did an interview to
that lady. She was supposed to get
married and the man left 2 weeks to
wedding. He left and went off. And at
that hour, she could not ask God any
question. She began to sing Digawa
Mwenawakwa. When Modwaire Listen, that's
a prophetic song that began to program.
Today, she's married. It began to order
her heavens. There is a battle that is
above you, but it's not above your
worship. Take your harp and your lyre.
Begin to prophesy. There is a generation
of Asaph. These are prophetic
worshipers.
You see the song we just did. Some of
those songs communicate realities to
men.
So, this what the Lord began to do. The
spirit came upon the tribe of Asaph. The
tribe of Asaph received the spirit and
they entered into their element of
playing a sound and manufacturing a
sound.
There are four things that answer for
you in the realm of the spirit. Your
worship, your praise, your prayer, and
your sacrifice. Those four answer for
you in the realm of the spirit. Let us
Let's deal with this matter quickly. The
spirit of the Lord came upon Jahaziel.
We are given the order. This was the
tribe of Asaph, prophetic worshipers.
Some of the Psalms are written by Asaph,
the Levitical order. I can teach a lot
about this matter. Worship was not for
gifted men. It was for Levites.
It was not for men who can go to TPF.
Worship was for Levites, people that had
a rank to stand and minister to God.
Why? Worship is not for congregation.
It's for God.
You must have capacity to minister to
God.
capacity
Why? Heaven is shut. No capacity. Locate
your bloodline in the spirit. Go to the
tribe of Asaph. Get their dealings in
the spirit. They were prophetic
worshipers. This is where David
manufactured the concept of playing a
harp and a spirit will lift all. It is
an anointing.
Levitical in nature.
praise and worship
I'm a winner with Zebulun, the business
tribe.
Let's continue quickly, please. Time
time. Everybody read. And he said,
"Listen, all of Judah and you
inhabitants of Jerusalem, and your King
Jehoshaphat, thus says the Lord to you,
do not be afraid." Everybody read.
Everybody read carefully.
I came to announce the same thing to
somebody.
There are battles that are in God
levels. And God is saying, "Do not be
afraid
because fear kicks out
faith. Nor be dismayed. Why? This battle
is not in your level. This battle is in
the God's level. This is where Psalms
46:10 came from. I will be still and
know that you are God. I know thy
character. You faileth not. You who
delivered me from Egypt, you still have
the power to fight enemies that have
pursued me in the place of my
establishment. You who has walked with
me, you still have the power to fight
this war. They have gathered against me,
oh God, but I know my arsenals and
weapons cannot fight this battle. I
choose to lift my eyes and begin to
sing. Let's look as we begin to conclude
this matter. See the weapons. The first
one was fasting and prayer.
The second one was Asaph worship.
Huh, quickly, sir.
16.
We need to hear about nutrition.
Some of us are eating everything.
Tomorrow, go down against them. They
will surely come up by the ascent of
Ziz, and you will find them at the end
of the brook before the wilderness of
Jeruel. Aha.
You will not need to fight. Everybody
read. You will not need to fight in this
battle. Position yourselves. Stand
still. Shut up at Aya. Oh my God, I will
show forth in the battlefield, but I
will have victory without war. I just
need to show up because there is a God
that fights our battles. Stand still and
see the salvation of the Lord, who is
with you, all Judah and Jerusalem. Do
not fear or be dismayed. Tomorrow, go
out against them for the Lord is with
you. I came to announce to somebody. The
Lord is saying, "Go out. The battle is
not mine. The battle is of the Lord. I
will stand still and know there is God."
Let's continue quickly. Quickly, let's
go to 18, my friend. And Jehoshaphat
bowed his head with his face to the
ground, and all Judah and the
inhabitants of Jerusalem bowed before
the Lord worshiping worshiping. What is
to worship? It's to tell God who he is.
You are mighty. You are sovereign. You
are the king of glory. You are glorious.
You are the mighty man of war. You can
never lose in any battle. That is how we
fight some of these battles. Not
complaining. Look at 19. Who created
watches? Then the Levites of the
children of the Kohathites and of the
children of the Korahites stood up and
did what? Praised the Lord God of Israel
with voices and loud loud and high.
Hallelujah.
Some of you we tell you to shout and you
are so moderate. We are the Munguana.
Let me tell you the victories. There is
a revelation of Kohathites and the
Korahites. They know there is a shout
that dismantles [screaming] the realm of
the spirit. There is a shout that
introduces fear in the camp of the
enemy. There is a shout shatta that
shakes the foundation of the wicked.
They began to praise. Are you seeing the
tools? They were in prayer. They fasted.
When they heard the Lord saying, "Stand
still," they knew we don't need stamina
in our flesh. We need stamina in our
spirit. How do I create capacity? By
prayer. I want to believe they were
speaking in tongues. They saw the enemy,
but they were saying, "Parosakata
Emparial Talapora." Because there is
something that gives you stamina in the
spirit.
In the realms of men, we look like we
are defeated. There's a song that says,
"I look like I'm surrounded, but I'm
surrounded by you."
Ah, Jesus, we may look like we are
surrounded, but we are surrounded by
him. Let's look at 20. There is These
are the things: praise, prayer, worship.
So, they rose early in the morning and
went out into the wilderness of Tekoa.
And as they went out, Jehoshaphat stood
and said, "Hear me, oh Judah, and you
inhabitants of Jerusalem. Believe in the
Lord your God." Everybody read. "And you
shall be established. Believe in the
prophets, and you shall do what?"
These were men that used to prophesy
with the harp.
We are about to finish church. Give me 2
minutes of a preacher.
Because next Sunday, I will not assure
you I'll have the same atmosphere.
Because you can you can preach the same
message, but it is atmospheres that
shift things in the spirit. Are you
getting me? Let's look Let's look at 21.
And when he had consulted with the
people, he appointed those who should
sing to the Lord, and who should praise
the beauty of holiness. And as they went
out before the armies, and were saying,
"Praise the Lord for his mercies
endureth forever." There is a victory
that comes by prayer, praise, and
fasting. When men understand this
strategy.
There are men that were given that work.
Let's look at 22.
Now, when they began to sing and to
praise, the Lord set
ambushes against the people of Ammon,
Moab, and Seir, who had come against
Judah, and they were
Jesus.
Jesus by prayer, by singing. Kaya
sataya. 23.
>> [snorts]
>> For the people of Ammon and Moab stood
up against the inhabitants of Mount Seir
to utterly kill and destroy them. And
when they had made an end of the
inhabitants of Seir, they had to destroy
one another. Listen, the Lord threw
chaos in their camp. They began to fight
one another. I know there are times we
always pray and say, "Let there be
confusion in the camp of the enemy." Oh,
these men showed up. There is a weapon
that shifts battle. It shifts from our
level to the level of God, and then
transfers the battle to the men that
were gathering against us. Let us stand
up on our feet.